<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alexey Gornostaev</title>
    <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content from Alexey Gornostaev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://alexeygornostaev.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gig workers are contemporary XX century factory workers</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2022-11-02-gig-workers-are-contemporary-factory-workers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2022-11-02-gig-workers-are-contemporary-factory-workers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My kid studies in a Russian online school. All classes are remote, 2 hours each, with 4 to 6 kids in a single class. The school operates akin to other modern Uber-like businesses. It connects students with teachers: collects the requests from parents, finds them a proper class, deals with payments processing and oversees the whole process to make it easier for both sides. It&amp;rsquo;s a valuable service and we were happy to find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been very surprised and uneasy to learn that a math teacher in a school like that earns just $5.5 an hour. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the salaries in rural parts of Russia, but in big cities teachers in schools earn much more than that. It&amp;rsquo;s an embarrassingly low sum of money with no employment protection and no benefits. Just as it is the case with the other gig workers: taxi drivers, on-demand couriers that bring you food, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies that operate those services are more often than not part of a very profitable big tech sector or venture funded with millions of dollars. You&amp;rsquo;d think they are not in need to squeeze every last penny from their workers. But that&amp;rsquo;s what they do. They want to grow fast and to do that they need to keep prices as low as possible, often much lower than the old way of getting these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These companies have complete control over business relationship between the worker and the user - they dictate the end user pricing and then decide how much on top of that they will leave for themselves, usually in a form of 30% commission. A teacher can&amp;rsquo;t decide how much to charge her students for the class. A teacher can&amp;rsquo;t cut her expenses by using cheaper payment providers or other backend services. The only way to earn more in such a system is to work more hours. As a result a more than 10 hour work day for a teacher or taxi-driver is a common case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation should not be considered normal. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of faith in tech companies finding and implementing a more fair system. They&amp;rsquo;ve already had a lot of time and experience dealing with various types of gig workers, but we are still here, with no improvement. On the contrary, more types of services are being digitized and new workers get the same unhealthy conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be regulated. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the exact solution, but we could start with a simple rule. If the end user price is set by the platform, then the platform must employ the worker, with all corresponding responsibilities. If the platform doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to employ the worker and is willing to continue to treat them as an independent contractor, then they should be free to charge the user for their services however they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the workers could choose between maybe lower salary, but with the protection and benefits of an actual employment or a higher paycheck on their own terms, if they believe that the service they are providing is better than the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure that we will look back at the early days of the gig economy as an unfair and shameful period. The same way we now think about the working conditions of the early XX century factory workers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux is simpler than macOS</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2022-07-16-linux-is-simpler-than-macos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2022-07-16-linux-is-simpler-than-macos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How far we&amp;rsquo;ve come that window management on modern Linux is simpler and more straightforward than in macOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In GNOME 42 all you need to learn is how to summon the Activities overview mode via hitting a button with a mouse or pressing a single (&amp;ldquo;super&amp;rdquo; by default) key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/gnome-shell.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;GNOME 42 Activities overview&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there you can do everything what you generally need to do with apps and window management: search for apps, see all the installed apps, manage your desktops and opened windows. One unified interface for all your window-related tasks. Learn one button and interface, and you&amp;rsquo;re good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Mac it&amp;rsquo;s burdensome to even count all the different ways to launch apps and operate windows that Apple invented and then added one more, and more, and more. All have their own distinctive interfaces, modes of operation and shortcuts to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dock to launch favourite apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spotlight to quickly launch any app and search for stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launchpad is an app that lists all your apps in an iOS-style modal view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mission control shows all opened windows and manages desktops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full screen and split view modes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stage manager lets you group windows together (I&amp;rsquo;ve thought this is what Spaces is for)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all this available choice, I personally still miss a core functionality and install a third-party app to get window snapping. Which, by the way, is available in GNOME out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A work of a distributed open source community is more coherent than a product of one of the most design oriented corporations in the world. Who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The ephemerality of mobile software</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-11-23-the-ephemerality-of-mobile-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-11-23-the-ephemerality-of-mobile-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/loom.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Loom screnshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve playedthrough Loom, a classic Lucas Arts adventure game, and it was fantastic to experience a 30 year old work of interactive software, that is easily playable today and has aged so gracefully. I guess, that level of accessibility is possible because of DOS, the operating system this game was designed for originally, being free to use and easy to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern mobile apps and games, on the contrary, vanish so quickly. Many many games even from a couple of years ago don’t work any more. On mobile, software has become ephemeral: the transition from 32 to 64 bit, the ever-changing system APIs, the rule that requires apps to make at least one update every two years if they don&amp;rsquo;t want to be delisted from the app store, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s very disappointing for future us. A whole generation of software could be completely lost. Loom proofs that good software design is timeless and should be preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What web3 and NFT could mean for video games</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-10-24-what-web3-could-mean-for-video-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-10-24-what-web3-could-mean-for-video-games/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about what could web3 and NFTs mean for video games. And, honestly, I can&amp;rsquo;t make myself to feel excited about the current crop of P2E games. There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-22-axie-infinity-economy-grind/&#34;&gt;a lot of economies in them and so little video games&lt;/a&gt;. Thoughts on how it could change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to understand how video game items differ from art, and why unlike in art, NFTs in video games can&amp;rsquo;t be a representation of ownership. Virtual items are made up with data from various different sources: art assets, code, database record, IP ownership, etc. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raphkoster.com/2021/10/21/ownership-how-virtual-worlds-work-part-5/&#34;&gt;Dive in&lt;/a&gt; to learn more. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With traditional video game items there is a central database that regulates who has access to what. When you buy an item, you essentially buy a service of creating a record in the database, which will grant you an access to an item. The properties of an item (how it looks, how it affects other objects) are controlled with code and assets, that are not part of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polygon.com/22709126/ethereum-creator-world-of-warcraft-nerf-nft-vitalik-buterin&#34;&gt;may change without the will of the &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which sometimes results in confusion and anger. And that&amp;rsquo;s understandable. A sword with specific look and properties had been showcased to a player and bought. Not an access pass to rent it, with the looks and stats that may or may not change in the future. That is a different deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In current blockchain games when you buy an item plus to an in-game representation of it you receive an NFT token, stored in your wallet, that is separate from the game. Basically, the ownership database record part of a virtual good is being detached and put in the space owned by a user. All the other item&amp;rsquo;s properties (art, code) continue to live, where they were before the NFT invention, at some server in US-EAST-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may be not a problem for art. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/punk6529/status/1451896453065023493&#34;&gt;You buy a token, that is a certificate of ownership&lt;/a&gt;. Whether you believe or not that the ownership is valuable is completely another matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for games it&amp;rsquo;s hugely important what something is: how it looks, works and behaves. See the before mentioned example with the nerfing of a WoW character. That&amp;rsquo;s why the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lootproject&#34;&gt;@lootproject&lt;/a&gt; is fascinating in that regard. It abstracts &amp;ldquo;how it looks and works&amp;rdquo; part, encouraging the community to come up with all sorts of different representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/loot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Loot bag&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they did. The community has built not only the representations for the loot itself, but has come up with characters (in several different stylistic choices), quests, maps and storylines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/lootproject.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Loot Project&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that here we can find a solution to the second part of the problem: how to grant an ownership to an item&amp;rsquo;s behaviour and its effects on the world around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I am sorry, you can&amp;rsquo;t. But, moving the work to public domain, freeing the community to create as many takes on the subject as they wish. What this achieves is making valuable not an exact representation of an item, but a concept of it. Which, if you think about it, is immensely powerful. The player could still own an item, or a numbered edition of it if she wishes and have an access to a range of practical implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general concept part is more valuable than one exact implementation. May be some variant will eventually become canon, but that is up to community to decide, anyone can fork the implementation and make adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/larsiusprime/status/1451629372293718020?s=20&#34;&gt;examples in video games&lt;/a&gt; that benefit from openness and where it is encouraged to mix, recreate and make collabs with characters and lore. All thanks to open source and public domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NFTs are all about making something scarce and limiting. But if you abstract enough and build on top of it, you could still have ownership of a virtual item and choose from a wide variety of fanfic implementations of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a PC</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-08-12-building-a-pc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-08-12-building-a-pc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Custom PC builds have come a long way since that last time I assembled my own PC, which was more than ten years ago. Every part of the experience is much nicer nowadays. A plethora of high quality parts is available: cases, power supplies, storage, ram, etc. The process of building has become simpler: you need less parts, these parts connect via compact cables that are easy to deal with, bulky and noisy cd-rom or spinning hard drives are not required anymore, the fans could be dead silent, if you want them to. And the best part remains: it&amp;rsquo;s as fun and satisfying as it always has been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current build, optimized for compactness, silent operation and light gaming:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streacom DA2 Mini-ITX case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMD Ryzen 4300GE with Noctua NH-U9S fan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ASRock B550 Phantom Gaming-ITX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32Gb RAM Samsung DDR4 3200&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250Gb SSD M.2 Samsung 970 Evo Plus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1Tb Samsung 870 Evo SATA SSD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corsair SF600 PSU&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also purchased a pair of standard Wi-Fi antennas, that need to be screwed in the ports. I like them better than a shark fin type one, that came with the motherboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case is about half of a 27&amp;quot; display in height. The side panels can be removed without a screwdriver.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/building-pc-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My new PC&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brackets can mount fans or different types of storage and be placed anywhere on the integrated track that runs along the frame of the case. Cable management is not my strong skill.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://alexeygornostaev.com/img/posts/building-pc-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My new PC (case opened)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I am really happy to revive an interest in an old hobby of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On instant games</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-27-on-instant-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-27-on-instant-games/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I get to know the best games from my 13-year-old daughter. Personally I mostly prefer uncool niche video games, but I get very excited when I learn about a game, that is played by every second kid in the neighbourhood, because these are the games that sometimes lead to dramatic changes in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the genre, visual or gameplay perspectives these games are often not mainstream. They&amp;rsquo;re not of the extremely popular MMO or first person shooter type. Visually they are very indie, but nevertheless, or maybe even because of that, capture the minds of kids. Usually, traditional video game press and websites learn about these games much later, only after they&amp;rsquo;ve reached the level of popularity, that can&amp;rsquo;t be ignored any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five Nights at Freddy&amp;rsquo;s (or FNAF to be short) was the first such game that I learned about from my kid, then there was Baldi&amp;rsquo;s Basics in Education and Learning (please, google what it looks like, I bet you&amp;rsquo;ll be surprised) and in the past year she played a lot of FRIDAY NIGHT FUNKIN&#39;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case of FRIDAY NIGHT FUNKIN&amp;rsquo; (that today is pretty well known in the industry) is so impressive that a new term has been invented to describe and distinguish modern web games from the old ones, that were somewhat similar, but made in Flash, rather than modern web technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An instant game is a game that can be played without a need to first download or install it, accessible on any device through a web browser, basically instantly available and playable via an ordinary web hyperlink. One could say the description more or less covers Flash games, social games of the pre-smartphone era and even has some hypercasual vibes in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why now? Well, because of the FRIDAY NIGHT FUNKIN&amp;rsquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s success story. Plus web technologies have matured enough: WebGL, fast CDN availability, video game engines with export for the Web, and a huge sea of available assets for creators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what&amp;rsquo;s more important, the world around us is finally ready to value games that are available just via a link. Video game streamers and tiktokers will definitely figure out how to entertain their audience with games that are accessible for everyone with a single click. Messenger apps, Reddit and Discord will help with the distribution and kill the need to deal with app stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could imagine that the unique capabilities of indie games will allow not only web ports of current titles, but completely new experiences that will be build on the core values of the web platform: accessibility, multiplayer-first, linkable not only the game itself, but the in-game and player content specifically, so that anyone can share an instantly viewable race replay with a call to action to beat it or a homebase in an open world game, that they&amp;rsquo;ve put dozens of hours into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It very well may be that we&amp;rsquo;ll also see new kinds of web video game showcases, which were numerous and popular back in the days. Though, if I had to guess, I&amp;rsquo;d bet that messenger apps would be a great fit for game discovery and social tools that are always needed for any kind of healthy video game ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, I am a believer in this possible future and would like to be part of it. Looking forward to the next game I&amp;rsquo;ll learn about from my kid.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Axie Infinity&#39;s economy is based on humans who do computer work</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-22-axie-infinity-economy-grind/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-22-axie-infinity-economy-grind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notboring.co/p/infinity-revenue-infinity-possibilities&#34;&gt;pay-to-earn Axie Infinity&lt;/a&gt; thing is curious, making a lot of money and you’ll absolutely hear about it soon from every corner of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t pretend I understand all of it. The game is simple (Pokemon style), the game economy is not. Though, one thing sounds like a complete red flag to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15% of Axie players cite the gameplay as their main motivation. Look, it’s a video game! That’s very low for a game and basically means that the game is not fun and people are there not for the game but for something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So i would guess that 15% are playing and all the others are grinding Axies (that’s what Pokemons are called here) for newcomers? To start playing the game a new player must purchase a set of Axies, that is a cornerstone of the game economy. So for every real player we have 6 workers who do the work to grind the assets for their master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional paid games this job is done by a computer automatically. Or the grinding process is actually fun which means that players are willing to do it, otherwise they would not play. In f2p games the grinding is slow, so that players either do it themselves or pay the developer to bypass it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, in crypto-games the grinding is so brutal, that the game has real humans who don&amp;rsquo;t play, but only grind and afterwards sell their work to humans who wish to start playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This looks like a master-servant relationship. And, actually, it is indeed. According to the article 60% of users are from The Philippines, grinding virtual heroes to sell and earning a few bucks more than on their real jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It even feels like we are going backwards in time! Progress is when we hire computers to do unnecessary monotonous work that was previously done by humans. And here it’s vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital stores influence authors creative decisions</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-21-digital-stores-influence-creative-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-21-digital-stores-influence-creative-decisions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Curious piece by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/johnnemann&#34;&gt;@johnnemann&lt;/a&gt; on the disadvantages that short niche games have on Steam.
I believe this is true for all current digital stores, not only games. And in turn it indeed changes creators behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify encourages to release tracks faster and more often. As a result we get more singles and remixes. Apple and Google stores encourage free apps that are monetized by either in-app purchases or subscriptions. Paid apps with single purchase are a fraction of the market. Certain types of apps and games are almost gone from mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dynamics favour continuous delivery of content which is preferably paid by micro-transactions or feels like free (read: is subscription-based). And in the end, that is all about user engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers prefer those changes, so the current model is here to stay. And niche/short/not “modern” product will have less exposure at the time when the stores will continue to capture as much of attention as they can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I obviously don’t know the answers, but in general i feel the market in addition to current stores will find a new model that will be better suited for creators of niche content. Because the demand is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If i had to guess, i would say that it will be a patreon/only fans/kickstarter like model where customers don’t pay for specific games but follow/subscribe to favourite developers with monthly payments and developers are creatively free to make whatever they wish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A round-up of the recent articles on where things are headed in video game space</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-03-roundup-articles-video-game-space-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-07-03-roundup-articles-video-game-space-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ll ask me what recent shifts in the video game industry I view as the most interesting and aspiring i&amp;rsquo;ll point you to these insightful observations made by other people:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/may/08/work-can-virtual-meeting-spaces-save-us-all-from-zoom-fatigue&#34;&gt;Can virtual meeting spaces save us all from Zoom fatigue?&lt;/a&gt; Pandemic has changed a lot of our social and work-related perceptions and it isn&amp;rsquo;t likely we&amp;rsquo;ll move back to how things were prior. We are rethinking the work processes: hybrid and remote work are the new normal, video call is the default way of having a meeting, and corporations now onboard many employees virtually rather than on-site. The tools we&amp;rsquo;ve created in the last decade worked for the most part and made the shift to remote work and social life painless, but we are still in the beginning and a lot of startups will focus on rethinking tools for communication and collaboration. Video game like social spaces are starting to emerge and use the advantages of spatial interfaces and game mechanics to bring  virtual closer to real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jonlai.co/game-like&#34;&gt;The Best Apps Today are
Games in Disguise&lt;/a&gt;. The best apps today use video game mechanics in their core product design. Fun is the new powermetric because users naturally gravitate to the most rewarding experience. When people have fun and feel they are achieving their goals, they build long-term habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://future.a16z.com/instant-games/&#34;&gt;The Future of Games Is Instant&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fortressofdoors.com/the-future-of-games-is-an-instant-flash-to-the-past/&#34;&gt;The Future of Games is an Instant Flash to the past&lt;/a&gt;. Could instant games, i.e games that are frictionless, instantly playable no matter the device, accessible through links, and cross-platform be the future and what the embedded social aspect of the web and hyperlynking will change about how we develop and distribute games?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fortressofdoors.com/so-you-want-to-compete-with-roblox/&#34;&gt;So You Want to Compete with Roblox&lt;/a&gt;. Roblox was numerous times mentioned during Apple/Epic trial and is one the most talked about companies in the industry. You also can&amp;rsquo;t exclude the topic of Roblox when talking about platforms, distribution, platform fees and tools for creators. Each of which is in itself one of the most think about topics in the industry right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is gamification</title>
      <link>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-06-08-what-is-gamification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexeygornostaev.com/posts/2021-06-08-what-is-gamification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently got interested in the topic of using game mechanics in consumer software products and stumbled upon an old, but still useful talk by Gabe Zichermann on gamification. Today gamification is not a trendy word as it used to be and it got somewhat spoiled by many basic and not well-thought-out implementations of achievements and leaderboards. However, the underlying principles are based on modern game design with the goal of making software more fun and the users more motivated. That task is as relevant as ever. I encourage you to find time and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6O1gNVeaE4g&amp;amp;t&#34;&gt;watch the whole talk&lt;/a&gt;. Below are my notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gamification is the process of using the game thinking and mechanics to engage audiences and solve problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If Shakespeare lived in the modern world he could say &amp;ldquo;All the world is a game&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are games about being a traffic controller, a farmer. Fun and theme are not related. Theme is a lure to bring people in. If a job of a traffic controller can be fun then anything could be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carmen vs. Sandiego released in the 80-s is still the last successful educational game. Why? Because parents and teachers became involved in designing games and kids smell that shit instantly. In parallel Civilzation and Sim City almost invisibly taught people basic history lessons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One could say that gamification is non-fiction gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick loyalty programs history:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1800s: tangible goods (buy 10 items get 1 free)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1930s: cash incentives (collect tickets when buying goods. almost like a virtual currency, hard to do the math for a consumer) -&amp;gt; collect X and then redeem them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1980s: loyalty systems (it&amp;rsquo;s about status more than about free stuff)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000s: virtual rewards (no real money as a reward, only a status).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no money out from Farmville or Foursquare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loyalty choices are now public. Because word of mouth is more predictable (Zynga knows how) than in the old days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gamification loop: challenges -&amp;gt; win conditions -&amp;gt; leaderboards -&amp;gt; badges -&amp;gt; social networking -&amp;gt; status. A point system at the heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users naturally gravitate to the most rewarding experience. By definition games have an advantage. They are designed to be rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main player types: achiever, explorer, killer and socializer.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;socializer: lightweight, non-confrontation, easy interactions. This is the most common one - around 80% of players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;achiever: beat the game, i want to win.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;explorer: find all the secrets and signal it to the crowd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;killer: i win, you loose. beat the opponent and signal it to the crowd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fun is the new powermetric. Because, as we&amp;rsquo;ve said earlier, -&amp;gt; users naturally gravitate to the most rewarding experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leaderboard in an arcade: top 20 scores. A user sees huge scores and doesn&amp;rsquo;t believe he can reach them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern leaderboard: no matter where a user really is in the leaderboard we show them in the middle, two friends below, two friends on top and a message what to do to move up. Exception: when a user is literally in top 20.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onboarding - is level 1. Player is put right away in a game, in a very controlled path with fast gratification, only after completing he is asked to register. Very different from the web landing sign up flow which usually starts with the registration step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every single touch point is an opportunity to convert a user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you interested in more of a motivational kind of talk on how video games can change the world for the better i recommend a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/jane_mcgonigal_gaming_can_make_a_better_world?language=en&#34;&gt;TED Talk by Jane McGonigal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>